Jambo, bonjour, zdravstvujtye, dayo: these are a few of the languages
جامبو ، بنجور ، زدرزافيت : "مرحبا بكم" في عدد قليل من اللغات
that I've spoken little bits of over the course of the last six weeks,
التي تحدث بها قليلا خلال الستة أسابيع الماضية
as I've been to 17 countries I think I'm up to, on this crazy tour I've been doing,
خلال جولتي في ١٧ دولة، أعتقد أنها جولة تكاد لا تُصدق
checking out various aspects of the project that we're doing.
وكنت خلالها اتفحص بعض جوانب المشروع الذي نقوم به
And I'm going to tell you a little bit about later on.
والتي سأخبركم عنها عما قليل
And visiting some pretty incredible places,
زرت اماكن في غاية الجمال والروعة
places like Mongolia, Cambodia, New Guinea, South Africa, Tanzania twice --
اماكن مثل منغوليا ، كمبوديا ، غينيا الجديدة ، جنوب افريقيا و تنزانيا مرتين
I was here a month ago.
كنت هنا قبل شهر واحد
And the opportunity to make a whirlwind tour of the world like that
اتيحت لي الفرصة لكي آتجول على العالم بسرعة خاطفة
is utterly amazing, for lots of reasons.
كانت جولة آخاذة لأسباب عديدة
You see some incredible stuff.
اولا ستشاهد الكثير من الاشياء العجيبة
And you get to make these spot comparisons
وستتمكن من ملاحظات الفروقات البارزة
between people all around the globe.
بين البشر من كل انحاء العالم
And the thing that you really take away from that,
والعبرة التي يمكن ان تستفيد منها
the kind of surface thing that you take away from it,
الشيء الواضح الذي يمكن ان تخرج به
is not that we're all one, although I'm going to tell you about that,
ليس أننا جميعا شيء واحد -رغم انني سأتحدث عن ذلك فيما بعد-
but rather how different we are.
ولكن كيف اننا مختلفون بشكل كبير
There is so much diversity around the globe.
هناك تنوع كبير جدا حول الكرة الارضية
6,000 different languages spoken by six and a half billion people,
٦٠٠٠ لغة مختلفة يتحدثها ستة مليارات ونصف من البشر
all different colors, shapes, sizes.
بجميع الالوان والاشكال والاحجام
You walk down the street in any big city, you travel like that,
عندما تمشي في اي شارع في مدينة كبرى ، ستحس كما لو انك كنت مسافرا
and you are amazed at the diversity in the human species.
وستندهش من مدى التنوع في اجناس البشر
How do we explain that diversity?
كيف يمكن ان نفسر كل هذا التنوع؟
Well, that's what I'm going to talk about today,
حسنا، هذا ما سأتحدث عنه اليوم
is how we're using the tools of genetics,
عن كيف نستخدم أدوات الهندسة الوراثية
population genetics in particular, to tell us how we generated this diversity,
مبادىء (الوراثة السكانية) على وجه الخصوص لكي تبين لنا مصدر هذا التنوع
and how long it took.
وكم استغرقت من الوقت لكي تحدث
Now, the problem of human diversity,
والآن، موضوع التنوع البشري
like all big scientific questions --
مثله مثل المواضيع العلمية الكبرى
how do you explain something like that --
وطريقة تفسيرها
can be broken down into sub-questions.
يمكن ان يتم عبر تقسيمها لأسئلة أصغر حجماً
And you can ferret away at those little sub-questions.
يمكنك بعدها ملاحقة تلك الأسئلة الفرعية
First one is really a question of origins.
أول سؤال هو في الحقيقة عن أصل البشر
Do we all share a common origin, in fact?
هل نحن جميعا نتشارك في الأصول فعلاً؟
And given that we do -- and that's the assumption
ولو وافقنا على ذلك ، وهذا هو الإفتراض السائد
everybody, I think, in this room would make -- when was that?
الذي يعتقد به كل من في هذه الغرفة ، فمتى كان ذلك؟
When did we originate as a species?
متى وُجد جنسنا البشري؟
How long have we been divergent from each other?
منذ متى ونحن نتفرع ونختلف عن بعضنا البعض؟
And the second question is related, but slightly different.
السؤال الثاني له علاقة بهذا الموضوع ولكن من زواية مختلفة
If we do spring from a common source,
لو اننا جميعا نأتي من مصدر واحد
how did we come to occupy every corner of the globe,
كيف تأتى لنا ان نحتل كل زواية في الكرة الأرضية؟
and in the process generate all of this diversity,
وخلال هذه العملية كان جنسنا البشري مستمر في عملية التنوع
the different ways of life, the different appearances,
بمظاهر وأشكال مختلفة في الحياة
the different languages around the world?
وبلغات مختلفة حول العالم
Well, the question of origins, as with so many other questions in biology,
حسنا، السؤال عن أصولنا مثله مثل العديد من الأسئلة في مجال علم الأحياء
seems to have been answered by Darwin over a century ago.
يبدو ان (داروين) قد اجاب عليها منذ قرن مضى
In "The Descent of Man," he wrote,
في كتابه (تاريخ الإنسان) كتب ما نصه
"In each great region of the world, the living mammals
" في كل منطقة كبيرة في العالم تبدو الثدييات
are closely related to the extinct species of the same region.
مرتبطة ارتباطا وثيقا بالاجناس المنقرضة في تلك المنطقة
It's therefore probable that Africa was formerly inhabited by extinct apes
ولهذا من المحتمل ان تكون أفريقيا كانت هي ملاذ القرود التي انقرضت
closely allied to the gorilla and chimpanzee,
والتي كانت قريبة من جنس (الغوريلا ) و (الشمبانزي)
and as these two species are now man's nearest allies,
واليوم يعتبر هذين الجنسين اقرب الحيوانات شبها للإنسان
it's somewhat more probable that our early progenitors
وبشكل أو بآخر من المحتمل ان اجدادنا السابقين
lived on the African continent than elsewhere."
عاشوا في قارة أفريقيا اكثر من اي مكان آخر .."
So we're done, we can go home -- finished the origin question.
لقد أجاب على سؤال اصول البشر ، يمكننا الذهاب لبيوتنا الآن
Well, not quite. Because Darwin was talking about our distant ancestry,
في الحقيقة ، ليس تماماً. لان (داروين) كان يتكلم عن اصولنا البعيدة جدا
our common ancestry with apes.
كان يتحدث عن اصلنا المشترك مع القرود
And it is quite clear that apes originated on the African continent.
ومن الواضح جدا ان القرود قد نشأت في قارة أفريقيا
Around 23 million years ago, they appear in the fossil record.
منذ قرابة ٢٣ مليون سنة ظهر لهم أثر في سجل الأحافير
Africa was actually disconnected from the other landmasses at that time,
وأفريقيا في ذلك الوقت كانت مفصولة ومستقلة عن باقي القارات
due to the vagaries of plate tectonics, floating around the Indian Ocean.
وبسبب التغييرات المفاجئة في صفيحات القارات ، طفت قارة افريقيا حول المحيط الهندي
Bumped into Eurasia around 16 million years ago,
واصطدمت بكتلة (اوروبا-آسيا) حوالي ١٦ مليون سنة خلت
and then we had the first African exodus, as we call it.
وحصلت اول هجرة أفريقية في ذلك الوقت
The apes that left at that time ended up in Southeast Asia,
القرود التي غادرت أفريقيا استقر بها المقام في جنوب شرق آسيا
became the gibbons and the orangutans.
واصبحت قرود (القابون) و (الاورانقتون)
And the ones that stayed on in Africa
اما تلك التي بقيت في أفريقيا
evolved into the gorillas, the chimpanzees and us.
تطورت لتصبح (غوريلات) و (شامبانزي) و (بشر)
So, yes, if you're talking about our common ancestry with apes,
ولهذا نستطيع القول ان اصلنا المشترك مع القرود
it's very clear, by looking at the fossil record, we started off here.
قد بدأ هنا في أفريقيا حسب سجلات الأحافير
But that's not really the question I'm asking.
ولكن في الحقيقة هذا ليس السؤال الذي سألته
I'm asking about our human ancestry,
أنا أسأل عن اصل البشر، أصلنا نحن
things that we would recognize as being like us
أسأل عن المخلوقات التي نتعرف على أنها مثلنا
if they were sitting here in the room.
تلك التي لو كانت معنا في تلك الغرفة
If they were peering over your shoulder,
وأطلت عليك من فوق كتفك
you wouldn't leap back, like that. What about our human ancestry?
لم تجعلك تقفز للخلف. ماذا عن أصلنا البشري؟
Because if we go far enough back,
لأننا لو رجعنا للماضي بما فيه الكفاية
we share a common ancestry with every living thing on Earth.
سنجد اننا نشترك في اصل واحد مع كل المخلوقات على وجه الكرة الأرضية
DNA ties us all together, so we share ancestry with barracuda
الحمض النووي (DNA) يربطنا جميعاً ، لدينا اصل مشترك مع سمك (الباركودا)
and bacteria and mushrooms, if you go far enough back -- over a billion years.
ولو رجعت في الماضي حوالي مليار سنة لوجدت ان لدينا اصل مشترك مع (البكتيريا) و (فطر المشروم)
What we're asking about though is human ancestry.
ومع ذلك فسؤالنا حول أصل البشر أنفسهم
How do we study that?
كيف يمكننا أن ندرس ذلك؟
Well, historically, it has been studied using the science of paleoanthropology.
تاريخيا، تمت دراسة هذا السؤال عبر علوم الأحافير والإنسان (الانثروبولجي)
Digging things up out of the ground,
يتم حفر والتنقيب عن الأحافير في الارض
and largely on the basis of morphology --
وبناء على الشكل الخارجي للأشياء
the way things are shaped, often skull shape -- saying,
مثل الشكل الخارجي لجمجمة نقول ..
"This looks a little bit more like us than that, so this must be my ancestor.
" هذه تبدو مشابه قليلا لجمجمة البشر اكثر من تلك الجمجمة، ولهذا ربما انها تخص احد اصولنا البشرية
This must be who I'm directly descended from."
لا بد انها تتعلق بالشخص الذي الذي يرجع إليه نسبي"
The field of paleoanthropology, I'll argue,
سأجادل في مجال علم أثار وأصول البشر
gives us lots of fascinating possibilities about our ancestry,
رغم انه يُمدنا بالكثير من الإحتماليات المدهشة حول أصولنا
but it doesn't give us the probabilities that we really want as scientists.
ولكنه لا يعطينا الإحتماليات التي يرغب فيها العلماء
What do I mean by that?
ماالذي أقصده بذلك؟
You're looking at a great example here.
أنتم تنظرون إلى مثال رائع هنا
These are three extinct species of hominids,
هناك ثلاثة اجناس بشرية منقرضة
potential human ancestors.
كلها تعتبر اصول محتملة للبشر
All dug up just west of here in Olduvai Gorge, by the Leakey family.
تم استخراج احافيرها في الجهة الغربية من هذا المكان في (أولديفي جورج) عبر عائلة (ليكي)
And they're all dating to roughly the same time.
وكلها ترجع الى نفس التاريخ تقريبا
From left to right, we've got Homo erectus, Homo habilis,
من اليسار لليمين لدينا (هومو اريكتس) ، (هومو هابليس)
and Australopithecus -- now called Paranthropus boisei,
و (أستراليوباثكس) ويسمى حاليا بـ (بارانثروبس بويسي)
the robust australopithecine. Three extinct species, same place, same time.
ثلاثة اجناس منقرضة في نفس المكان ونفس الزمان
That means that not all three could be my direct ancestor.
هذا يعني انها بالتأكيد ليست كلها اصول البشر المباشرة
Which one of these guys am I actually related to?
إلى اي من هؤلاء الثلاثة أنتمي؟
Possibilities about our ancestry, but not the probabilities that we're really looking for.
ما هي الإحتماليات؟ ولكن الاحتماليات ليست هي ما نود البحث عنه.
Well, a different approach has been to look at morphology in humans
حسنا، هناك طريقة مختلفة تم استخدامها لمقارنة الشكل الخارجي للبشر
using the only data that people really had at hand until quite recently --
عبر استخدام المعلومات التي يملكونها حتى وقت قريب
again, largely skull shape.
ومرة أخرى ، عبر (الشكل الخارجي للجمجمة)
The first person to do this systematically was Linnaeus,
اول شخص قام بذلك بشكل علمي كان (ليناويس)
Carl von Linne, a Swedish botanist,
(كارل فون لين ) عالم نبات سويدي
who in the eighteenth century took it upon himself
والذي في القرن الثامن عشر اخذ على عاتقه
to categorize every living organism on the planet.
ان يقسم كل مخلوقات الارض في أقسام وفصائل
You think you've got a tough job?
تعتقدون انها مهمه صعبة؟
And he did a pretty good job.
لقد قام بعمل جيد جدا
He categorized about 12,000 species in "Systema Naturae."
قام بتقسيم ما يقارب ١٢،٠٠٠ جنس في مجلة (الطبيعة)
He actually coined the term Homo sapiens -- it means wise man in Latin.
وهو في الحقيقة من إبتكر مصطلح (هومو سابينس) والذي يعني (الرجل الحكيم) في اللاتينية
But looking around the world at the diversity of humans, he said,
ولكن عندما نظر إلى التنوع المدهش في البشر قال
"Well, you know, we seem to come in discreet sub-species or categories."
نحن كبشر ، يبدو كما لو إننا ننقسم إلى مجموعات فرعية واضحة
And he talked about Africans and Americans and Asians and Europeans,
وتكلم عن الأفارقة والأمريكين والآسيويين و الأوروبيين
and a blatantly racist category he termed "Monstrosus,"
وفئة سماها بعنصرية بغيضة (المتوحشون)
which basically included all the people he didn't like,
والتي ببساطة تشمل كل من لم يعجبه
including imaginary folk like elves.
بما في ذلك بعض المخلوقات الخيالية مثل (الإلف) (قصارالقامة ولهم اذان مدببة)
It's easy to dismiss this as the perhaps well-intentioned
يمكن ايجاد العذر له بحسن نيته
but ultimately benighted musings of an eighteenth century scientist
ولكن في نهاية المطاف فقد كان متأثرا بالعصور المظلمه في القرن الثامن عشر
working in the pre-Darwinian era.
في فترة ما قبل عصر (داروين)
Except, if you had taken physical anthropology
لكن لو درست علم أصل الانسان (الانثروبولوجي)
as recently as 20 or 30 years ago, in many cases you would have learned
قبل حوالي ٢٠-٣٠ سنة، ستجد في العديد من الحالات
basically that same classification of humanity.
أن في التقسيم البيولوجي للبشر
Human races that according to physical anthropologists of 30, 40 years ago --
الأجناس البشرية وفقا للأنثرولوجيين من 30 أو 40 عاما
Carlton Coon is the best example --
-من أمثال كارلتون كون-
had been diverging from each other -- this was in the post-Darwinian era --
قد انبثقت من بعضها -وهذه نظرة فترة من بعد دارون-
for over a million years, since the time of Homo erectus.
لما يزيد عن مليون سنة منذ أيام "الإنسان المنتصب"
But based on what data?
لكن بناء على أي بيانات؟
Very little. Very little. Morphology and a lot of guesswork.
بيانات قليلة، قليلة جدا، من علم التشكل أو "مورفولوجيا" والكثير من التخمين.
Well, what I'm going to talk about today,
حسنا، ما سأحدثكم اليوم عنه،
what I'm going to talk about now is a new approach to this problem.
ما سأتحدث عنه الآن، هو نظرة جديدة لهذه المشكلة
Instead of going out and guessing about our ancestry,
فعوضا عن التخمين حول أصولنا،
digging things up out of the ground, possible ancestors,
وحفر واستخراج أشياء من الأرض، بحثا عن أسلافٍ
and saying it on the basis of morphology --
بناء على "المورفولوجيا"
which we still don't completely understand,
والتي لا نزال لا نحيط بها علما،
we don't know the genetic causes underlying this morphological variation --
فنحن لا نعي الأسباب الجينية لهذا التنوع التشكيلي
what we need to do is turn the problem on its head.
ما نحتاج للقيام به عوضا عن ذلك، هو قلب المشكلة رأسا على عقب
Because what we're really asking is a genealogical problem,
لأننا في الحقيقة نحل مشكلة منطقية جينية
or a genealogical question.
أو نسأل سؤالا جينيا منطقيا
What we're trying to do is construct a family tree for everybody alive today.
ما نحاول فعله هو بناء شجرة عائلية لكل إنسان حي اليوم،
And as any genealogist will tell you --
وكأي عالم أنساب
anybody have a member of the family, or maybe you
أو فرد من أسرة ما، أو ربما أنت
have tried to construct a family tree, trace back in time?
قد جربت بناء شجرة عائلية، فتقوم بالتتبع في الزمن للوراء،
You start in the present, with relationships you're certain about.
فتبدأ بالحاضر والعلاقات المؤكدة لك،
You and your siblings, you have a parent in common.
أنت وأشقائك، والداك
You and your cousins share a grandparent in common.
أنت وأبناء عمومتك، وجدكم
You gradually trace further and further back into the past,
وتبدأ هكذا رجوعا في الماضي
adding these ever more distant relationships.
مضيفا تلك العلاقات البعيدة
But eventually, no matter how good you are at digging up the church records,
لكن في النهاية، مهما كنت ماهرا في البحث في السجلات،
and all that stuff, you hit what the genealogists call a brick wall.
ستصدم بما يطلق عليه علماء الأنساب: الحائط
A point beyond which you don't know anything else about your ancestors,
نقطة لا تعلم ما بعدها أي شيء عن أسلافك
and you enter this dark and mysterious realm we call history
وتكون قد دخلتَ كهف التاريخ المظلم
that we have to feel our way through with whispered guidance.
الذي نحتاج لتحسس طريقنا بالهمسات الخافتة
Who were these people who came before?
من هؤلاء الأشخاص الذين أتوا من قبلنا؟
We have no written record. Well, actually, we do.
ليس لدينا أي سجلات مكتوبة. حسنا، في حقيقة لدينا.
Written in our DNA, in our genetic code --
مكتوبة في الحمض النووي، في شفراتنا الجينية
we have a historical document that takes us back in time
لدينا مخطوطة تاريخبة تأخذنا في الزمان للوراء
to the very earliest days of our species. And that's what we study.
إلى الأيام الأولى من أسلافنا، وهذا ما نريد دراسته
Now, a quick primer on DNA.
والآن لمحة سريعة عن الحمض النووي.
I suspect that not everybody in the audience is a geneticist.
أتوقع أن لا يوجد بيننا عالم جينات
It is a very long, linear molecule, a coded version
إنه فتيل خطي طويلة مشفر
of how to make another copy of you. It's your blueprint.
بالمعلومات لصنع نسخ منك، إنه تصميمك الأولي
It's composed of four subunits: A, C, G and T, we call them.
إنه مكون من أربع وحدات: أيه سي جي وتي، كما نسميهم
And it's the sequence of those subunits that defines that blueprint.
وترتيب هذه الوحدات هو ما يعرف هذا التصميم الأولي
How long is it? Well, it's billions of these subunits in length.
كم طوله؟ حسنا إن عبارة عن مليارات من هذه الوحدات طولا
A haploid genome -- we actually have two copies of all of our chromosomes --
إنه جينوم مفرد، في الحقيقة لدينا نسختين من جميع كروموسوماتنا
a haploid genome is around 3.2 billion nucleotides in length.
إن جينوما فردانيا عبارة عن 3،2 مليار نيوكليوتيد طولا
And the whole thing, if you add it all together,
وإذا جمعت النسختين سوياً
is over six billion nucleotides long.
تحصل على ما يزيد عن 6 مليار نيوكليوتيد
If you take all the DNA out of one cell in your body,
إذا أخذت الحمض النووي من خلية واحدة من جسمك
and stretch it end to end, it's around two meters long.
وفردتها من طرف لآخر، وصلت إلى مترين طولا
If you take all the DNA out of every cell in your body,
وإذا أخذت الحمض النووي من كل خلية من جسمك
and you stretch it end to end, it would reach from here to the moon and back,
وفردتها طرفا لطرف، لوصلت إلى القمر وعادت
thousands of times. It's a lot of information.
آلاف المرات، إنه كم مهول من المعلومات
And so when you're copying this DNA molecule to pass it on, it's a pretty tough job.
لذا عندما تنسخ جزيء الحمض النووي، فأنت تقوم بعمل صعب
Imagine the longest book you can think of, "War and Peace."
تخيل أكبر كتاب هناك: ;كتاب الحرب والسلام (1500 صفحة)
Now multiply it by 100.
والآن اضرب الرقم بمئة
And imagine copying that by hand.
وتخيل نسخ ذلك بيدك
And you're working away until late at night,
وأنت تعمل ساهرا في الليل
and you're very, very careful, and you're drinking coffee
بينما أنت حذر جدا جدا، وتشرب القهوة
and you're paying attention, but, occasionally,
وتولي المهمة انتباهك، أحيانا
when you're copying this by hand,
عندما تنسخ بيدك
you're going to make a little typo, a spelling mistake --
ستقع في خطأ مطبعي، خطأ إملائي
substitute an I for an E, or a C for a T.
مبدلا حرفا بحرف
Same thing happens to our DNA as it's being passed on through the generations.
ونفس الشيء يحصل من الحمض النووي عندما يورث خلال الأجيال.
It doesn't happen very often. We have a proofreading mechanism built in.
ولكنه لا يحصل مرات عديدة، لأن لدينا ألية لتفادي الأخطاء
But when it does happen, and these changes get transmitted down
ولكن عندما يحصل الخطأ، يورث هذا الخطأ
through the generations, they become markers of descent.
خلال الأجيال، تاركة علامة فارقة
If you share a marker with someone,
وإذا كنت تشارك أحدا في علامة فارقة
it means you share an ancestor at some point in the past,
فهذا يعني أنك تشارك في جد في نقطة ما في الماضي.
the person who first had that change in their DNA.
الجد الذي حصل فيه التغيير الأول للحمض النووي
And it's by looking at the pattern of genetic variation,
فمن خلال التمعن في الفروقات الجينية
the pattern of these markers in people all over the world,
ونظم هذه الفروقات في أرجاء المعمورة
and assessing the relative ages when they occurred throughout our history,
وتقييم العصور المتناسبة لحصول هذه الفروقات خلال تاريخنا
that we've been able to construct a family tree for everybody alive today.
نستطيع بناء شجرة عائلية لكل من هو حي اليوم
These are two pieces of DNA that we use quite widely in our work.
هذان جزءان من الحمض النووي نستخدمهما في عملنا
Mitochondrial DNA, tracing a purely maternal line of descent.
الحمض النووي الميتوكوندريائي، يعود بنا خط أمومي
You get your mtDNA from your mother, and your mother's mother,
تحصل على الحمض النووي الميتوكوندريائي من أمك وهي من أمها
all the way back to the very first woman.
هكذا رجوعا إلى الامرأة الأولى
The Y chromosome, the piece of DNA that makes men men,
كروموسوم الواي، قطعة الحمض النووي الثانية التي تجعل من الرجل رجلاً
traces a purely paternal line of descent.
ترسم خطا أبويا لأسلافنا،
Everybody in this room, everybody in the world,
كل من في الغرفة، كل من في العالم
falls into a lineage somewhere on these trees.
يقع في مكان ما في هذه الأشجار
Now, even though these are simplified versions of the real trees,
الآن، وإن كانت هذه صورا مبسطة للأشجار الحقيقة
they're still kind of complicated, so let's simplify them.
فهي لا تزال معقدة، لذا لنبسطها أكثر
Turn them on their sides, combine them so that they look like a tree
لنقلبها على جنبها، ونجمعهم ليشكلوا شجرة
with the root at the bottom and the branches going up.
بجذور في الأسفل وفروع بالأعلى
What's the take-home message?
ما هو بيت القصيد؟
Well, the thing that jumps out at you first
حسنا، أول ما يبادر ذهنك
is that the deepest lineages in our family trees
أن أعمق الجذور في أشجار عوائلنا
are found within Africa, among Africans.
موجودة في أفريقيا وسط الأفارقة
That means that Africans have been accumulating
هذا يعني أن الأفارقة قد جمعوا
this mutational diversity for longer.
هذا التنوع الطفري منذ زمن
And what that means is that we originated in Africa. It's written in our DNA.
وما يعني أننا نعود في أصلنا إلى أفريقيا، وهذا ما ينص عليه الحمض النووي.
Every piece of DNA we look at has greater diversity within Africa than outside of Africa.
كل قطعة من الحمض النووي لها تنوع أكبر في أفريقيا مقارنة بغيرها
And at some point in the past, a sub-group of Africans
وعند نقطة ما تركت مجموعة من الأفارقة
left the African continent to go out and populate the rest of the world.
أفريقيا ليعمروا باقي العالم
Now, how recently do we share this ancestry?
الآن، منذ متي ونحن نتشارك في هذه السلالة؟
Was it millions of years ago, which we might suspect
هل كانت منذ ملايين السنين كما نظن
by looking at all this incredible variation around the world?
عندما نتأمل كل هذا التنوع حول العالم؟
No, the DNA tells a story that's very clear.
كلا، الحمض النووي يروي لنا قصة صريحة
Within the last 200,000 years, we all share an ancestor, a single person --
خلال الـ 200 ألف عام الماضية، كلنا اشتركنا في جد واحد، شخص واحد
Mitochondrial Eve, you might have heard about her -- in Africa,
أم الميتوكوندريائية، من أفريقيا
an African woman who gave rise to all the mitochondrial diversity in the world today.
امرأة أفريقية بها بدأ كل التنوع الميتوكوندريائي في العالم
But what's even more amazing
ولكن ما هو أكثر ادهاشا،
is that if you look at the Y-chromosome side,
هو أنك لو تمعنت في كروموسوم الواي
the male side of the story, the Y-chromosome Adam
الطرف الذكري من الرواية، آدم
only lived around 60,000 years ago.
لوجدت أنه عاش منذ 60 ألف عام فقط
That's only about 2,000 human generations,
أي ما يعادل 2000 جيل بشري
the blink of an eye in an evolutionary sense.
ما لا يعادل إلا لمحة في الحس التطوري
That tells us we were all still living in Africa at that time.
هذا يروي لنا أننا ما زلنا نعيش في أفريقيا حتى ذاك الوقت
This was an African man who gave rise
لقد كان رجلا أفريقيا
to all the Y chromosome diversity around the world.
الذي بدأ به كل تنوع كروموسوم الواي حول العالم
It's only within the last 60,000 years
فقط في الستين ألف سنة الماضية
that we have started to generate this incredible diversity we see around the world.
قد بدأنا لتوليد هذا التنوع المهول حول العالم
Such an amazing story.
يا لها من قصة مذهلة
We're all effectively part of an extended African family.
كلنا جزء فعال من هذه الأسرة الأفريقية الموسعة
Now, that seems so recent. Why didn't we start to leave earlier?
حسنا، هذا يبدو متأخرا جدا، لماذا لم نبدأ بالرحيل مبكرا؟
Why didn't Homo erectus evolve into separate species,
لماذا لم يتطور الإنسان المنتصب إلى فصائل مختلفة؟
or sub-species rather, human races around the world?
أو إلى فصائل فرعية حول العالم؟
Why was it that we seem to have come out of Africa so recently?
لماذا يبدو أننا قد خرجنا من أفريقيا من زمن قريب جدا؟
Well, that's a big question. These "why" questions,
حسنا، إن هذا سؤال كبير، إن أسئلة "لماذا" هذه
particularly in genetics and the study of history in general, are always the big ones,
خاصة في الجينات والتاريخ عموما، لطالما كانت أسئلة كبيرة!
the ones that are tough to answer.
التي تكون الأصعب للإجابة عنها
And so when all else fails, talk about the weather.
لذا عندما تغلق كل الأبواب، نتحدث عن الطقس!
What was going on to the world's weather around 60,000 years ago?
ما كان حال الطقس العالمي من 60000 سنة؟
Well, we were going into the worst part of the last ice age.
حسنا، كنا نمر بأسوأ مرحلة من العصر الجليدي الأخير
The last ice age started roughly 120,000 years ago.
والذي بدأ من 120000 سنة
It went up and down, and it really started to accelerate around 70,000 years ago.
وكان متقلبا حتى بدأ يشتد منذ حوالي 70000 سنة مضت
Lots of evidence from sediment cores
ويوجد العديد من الأدلة من بقايا الرواسب
and the pollen types, oxygen isotopes and so on.
وأنواع اللقاح، وحتى نظائر الأكسجين وغيرها على ذلك
We hit the last glacial maximum around 16,000 years ago,
وصلنا إلى أشد مرحلة جليدية منذ 16000 سنة
but basically, from 70,000 years on, things were getting really tough,
التي بدأت بالاشتداد أصلا من 70000 سنة
getting very cold. The Northern Hemisphere had massive growing ice sheets.
كان البرد قارصا، والنصف الشمالي امتلأ بالصفائح الجليدية
New York City, Chicago, Seattle, all under a sheet of ice.
نيويورك، شيكاجو، وسياتل كلها غطاها الجليد
Most of Britain, all of Scandinavia, covered by ice several kilometers thick.
معظم بريطانيا، وجميع إسكيندينافيا، غطتها بضعة كيلومترات من الجليد
Now, Africa is the most tropical continent on the planet --
الأن، أفريقيا هي أكثر القارات استوائية على الكوكب،
about 85 percent of it lies between Cancer and Capricorn --
حوالي 85% منها يقع بين خطي السرطان والجدي
and there aren't a lot of glaciers here,
ولا يكاد يوجد أي أنهار جليدية هناك
except on the high mountains here in East Africa.
بغض الطرف عن جبال شرق أفريقيا المرتفعة
So what was going on here? We weren't covered in ice in Africa.
إذا ما الذي يحصل ها هنا؟ نحن ببساطة لسنا مغطين بالجليد بأفريقيا
Rather, Africa was drying out at that time.
بل حتى أن أفريقيا كانت تعاني الجفاف وقتها
This is a paleo-climatological map
هذه خريطة ترسم الطقس التاريخي للأرض
of what Africa looked like between 60,000 and 70,000 years ago,
وتظهر منظر أفريقيا ما بين 60000 و70000 سنة مضت
reconstructed from all these pieces of evidence that I mentioned before.
وهي مبنية من الأدلة التي ذكرتها من قليل
The reason for that is that ice actually sucks moisture out of the atmosphere.
والسبب وراء الجفاف هو أن الجليد يسحب الرطوبة من الجو
If you think about Antarctica, it's technically a desert, it gets so little precipitation.
إذا فكرت بأنتارتيكا، ستجد أنها صحراء لا تمطر
So the whole world was drying out.
إذا، فالعالم كله كان يجف
The sea levels were dropping. And Africa was turning to desert.
مستوى البحر ينخفض، وأفريقيا تتحول إلى صحراء
The Sahara was much bigger then than it is now.
إن الصحراء الكبرى كانت أكبر بكثير مما هي عليه اليوم
And the human habitat was reduced to just a few small pockets,
والمساكن البشرية انحصرت في مناطق قليلة صغيرة
compared to what we have today.
مقارنة بما لدينا اليوم
The evidence from genetic data
إن الأدلة من البيانات الجينية
is that the human population around this time, roughly 70,000 years ago,
تبين أن السكان البشر من 70000 سنة
crashed to fewer than 2,000 individuals.
انحدر دون الألفين نسمة
We nearly went extinct. We were hanging on by our fingernails.
لقد أوشكنا على الانقراض، كنا متمسكين بقشة!
And then something happened. A great illustration of it.
وثم حصل أمر ما، وهذا استعراض له
Look at some stone tools.
انظر إلى بعض هذه الأدوات الحجرية
The ones on the left are from Africa, from around a million years ago.
التي على اليسار من أفريقيا، ويقارب عمرها المليون سنة
The ones on the right were made by Neanderthals, our distant cousins,
التي على اليسار صنعها البشر البدائيون، أبناء عمومتنا
not our direct ancestors, living in Europe,
الذين من أوروبا، وليس أسلافنا،
and they date from around 50,000 or 60,000 years ago.
وعمرهم ما يقارب ما 50000 أو 60000 سنة
Now, at the risk of offending any paleoanthropologists
الآن، سأخاطر بإهانة عالم أصول البشر
or physical anthropologists in the audience,
أو عالم حيوية الإنسان من الحاضرين،
basically there's not a lot of change between these two stone tool groups.
بصفة أساسية لا فرق يلاحظ بين مجموعتي الأحجار.
The ones on the left are pretty similar to the ones on the right.
التي على اليسار تشبه التي على اليمين.
We are in a period of long cultural stasis from a million years ago
نحن في حالة ركود حضاري طويل منذ مليون سنة
until around 60,000 to 70,000 years ago.
إلى ما بين 60000 و 70000 ألف سنة مضت.
The tool styles don't change that much.
إن تصميم الأدوات يكاد لم يتغير
The evidence is that the human way of life
الدليل هو أن حياة البشر
didn't change that much during that period.
لم تتغير كثيرا طوال تلك الفترة
But then 50, 60, 70 thousand years ago, somewhere in that region,
لكن منذ 50، 60، أو 70 ألف سنة، في مكان في تلك المنطقة
all hell breaks loose. Art makes its appearance.
انفلتت الأمور، تفجرت الفنون!
The stone tools become much more finely crafted.
بدأت الأدوات الحجرية تنحت بمهارة
The evidence is that humans begin to specialize in particular prey species,
ما دل أن البشر بدؤوا بعملية التخصص في أصناف معينة
at particular times of the year.
من الفرائس وفقا لموسم السنة
The population size started to expand.
التعداد السكاني بدأ بالتوسع
Probably, according to what many linguists believe,
غالبا، ووفقا لما يعتقد العديد من اللغويين
fully modern language, syntactic language -- subject, verb, object --
لغة حديثة مكتملة، لغة نحوية: فعل وفاعل، مبتدأ وخبر
that we use to convey complex ideas, like I'm doing now, appeared around that time.
مثل التي نستعملها لإيصال الأفكار المعقدة، ظهرت تلك اللغة في ذلك الوقت
We became much more social. The social networks expanded.
أصبحنا اجتماعيين أكثر، وبدأت الشبكات الاجتماعية بالتوسع
This change in behavior allowed us to survive these worsening conditions in Africa,
إن هذا التغير في السلوك هو ما سمح لنا بالبقاء رغم تلك الظروف المتساوئة في أفريقيا
and they allowed us to start to expand around the world.
وسمح أيضا لنا بالتوسع حول العالم
We've been talking at this conference about African success stories.
لقد كنا نتحدث في هذا المؤتمر عن قصص النجاح الأفريقية
Well, you want the ultimate African success story?
حسنا، أتريدون القصة الأفريقية الأنجح؟
Look in the mirror. You're it. The reason you're alive today
انظروا في المرآة، إنها أنتم، إن السبب في أنك حي اليوم
is because of those changes in our brains that took place in Africa --
يرجع إلى تلك التغييرات التي حدثت لأدمغتنا في أفريقيا
probably somewhere in the region where we're sitting right now,
غالبا في المكان الذي تجلس فيه في هذه اللحظة
around 60, 70 thousand years ago --
قبل 60 أو 70 ألف سنة
allowing us not only to survive in Africa, but to expand out of Africa.
ما سمح لنا ليس بالبقاء في أفريقيا فحسب، بل بالتوسع خارج أفريقيا
An early coastal migration along the south coast of Asia,
وهكذا بدأت هجرة ساحلية على طول الساحل الجنوبي لأسيا،
leaving Africa around 60,000 years ago,
تاركة أفريقيا منذ حوالي 60000 سنة
reaching Australia very rapidly, by 50,000 years ago.
واصلة إلى أستراليا قبل 50000 سنة من الآن
A slightly later migration up into the Middle East.
وهجرة أخرى تلتها ولكن إلى الشرق الأوسط
These would have been savannah hunters.
وكان فيها صيادوا السافانا،
So those of you who are going on one of the post-conference tours,
لذا من كان منكم سيذهب إلى أحد جولات ما بعد المؤتمر
you'll get to see what a real savannah is like.
سيرى كيف تكون السافانا،
And it's basically a meat locker.
إنها ببساطة خزنة للحوم!
People who would have specialized in killing the animals,
إن الأشخاص الذي تخصصوا في صيد الحيوانات
hunting the animals on those meat locker savannahs, moving up,
تتبعوا الفرائس صعودا إلى الشمال عبر خزائن لحوم السافانا
following the grasslands into the Middle East around 45,000 years ago,
هكذا وصولا إلى الشرق الأوسط منذ حوالي 45000 سنة
during one of the rare wet phases in the Sahara.
خلال أحد الفترات النادرة المطيرة للصحراء الكبرى
Migrating eastward, following the grasslands,
مهاجرين شرقا عبر الأراضي العشبية
because that's what they were adapted to live on.
لأنها كانت ملائمة لهم ولطريقة حياتهم،
And when they reached Central Asia,
وأخيرا وصلوا إلى وسط آسيا
they reached what was effectively a steppe super-highway,
وهكذا وصلوا إلى ما كان بمثابة طريق سريع،
a grassland super-highway.
طريق سريع عشبي.
The grasslands at that time -- this was during the last ice age --
لقد امتدت الأراضي العشبية، خلال ما كان العصر الجليدي الأخير،
stretched basically from Germany all the way over to Korea,
من ألمانيا إلى كوريا عابرة كل تلك الأراضي
and the entire continent was open to them.
وهكذا كانت القارة بأكملها مفتوحة لهم.
Entering Europe around 35,000 years ago,
دخلوا أوروبا منذ 35000 سنة
and finally, a small group migrating up
وأخيرا، هاجرت مجموعة صغيرة
through the worst weather imaginable, Siberia,
خلال أسوأ طقس ممكن -طقس سايبيريا-
inside the Arctic Circle, during the last ice age --
عابرين الدائرة القطبية خلال العصر الجليدي الأخير
temperature was at -70, -80, even -100, perhaps --
بدرجات حرارة قد تكون بلغت 60 أو 70 درجة مئوية تحت الصفر،
migrating into the Americas, ultimately reaching that final frontier.
مهاجرين إلى الأمريكيتين، وبهذا وصلت رحلتهم حدها الأخير.
An amazing story, and it happened first in Africa.
قصة مذهلة، وكلها بدأت من أفريقيا.
The changes that allowed us to do that,
هذه التغيرات التي سمحت لنا عمل هذا،
the evolution of this highly adaptable brain that we all carry around with us,
إن تطور هذا الدماغ الجيد التأقلم الذي نحمل معنا،
allowing us to create novel cultures,
هو ما سمح لنا بإبداع هذه الحضارات المستحدثة،
allowing us to develop the diversity
وما خلق كل هذا التنوع
that we see on a whirlwind trip like the one I've just been on.
الذي نراه في رحلة مثل التي ذهبتها للتو.
Now, that story I just told you is literally a whirlwind tour
إن القصة التي رويتها للتو لكم هي حرفيا رحلة زوبعية
of how we populated the world, the great Paleolithic wanderings of our species.
فيها عمرنا الأرض، إنها الرحلة العظيمة من العصر الحجري لجنسنا البشري،
And that's the story that I told a couple of years ago
وتلك القصة قد رويتها منذ سنتين
in my book, "The Journey of Man," and a film that we made with the same title.
في كتابي "رحلة الإنسان"، وفيلمي الذي حمل نفس العنوان،
And as we were finishing up that film --
وبينما كنا نكمل الفيلم
it was co-produced with National Geographic --
-الذي أنتج بالشراكة مع "ناشنال جيوغرافيك"-
I started talking to the folks at NG about this work.
بدأت محادثات مع أشخاص من "ناشونال جيوغرافيك" عن هذا العمل
And they got really excited about it. They liked the film, but they said,
وقد تحمسوا بشأن الموضوع، لقد أعجبهم الفيلم، ولكنهم قالوا:
"You know, we really see this as kind of
"أتعلم؟ لقد أعجبنا هذا النوع
the next wave in the study of human origins, where we all came from,
الجديد من دراسة الأصول البشرية، وأين منشؤنا
using the tools of DNA to map the migrations around the world.
باستخدام الحمض النووي لرسم خريطة لهجراتنا حول العالم،
You know, the study of human origins is kind of in our DNA,
أتعلم؟ إن دراسة أصولنا هو نوعاً ما جزء من الحمض النووي خاصتنا
and we want to take it to the next level.
ونحن نريد السعي إلى الخطوة التالية،
What do you want to do next?"
ما التالي الذي تريد عمله؟"
Which is a great question to be asked by National Geographic.
لقد كان سؤال رائعا من قبل "ناشونال جيوغرافيك"،
And I said, "Well, you know, what I've sketched out here is just that.
فقلت لهم أن ما قمت به هو مسودة،
It is a very coarse sketch of how we migrated around the planet.
وهو مسودة غير مصقولة لهجراتنا حول العالم،
And it's based on a few thousand people we've sampled from,
وهي مبنية على عينة من بضعة آلاف من البشر فحسب،
you know, a handful of populations around the world.
وهي تشكل حفنة من سكان العالم،
Studied a few genetic markers, and there are lots of gaps on this map.
ولا يزال الكثير من الفراغات في الخريطة،
We've just connected the dots. What we need to do
لقد وصلنا نقاطا فقط، وعلينا أن
is increase our sample size by an order of magnitude or more --
نزيد حجم العينة بعدة مرات،
hundreds of thousands of DNA samples from people all over the world."
مئات الآلاف من عينات الدي أن أي من أشخاص من كل أنحاء العالم،
And that was the genesis of the Genographic Project.
وهكذا خلق مشروع الجيني الجغرافي،
The project launched in April 2005.
انطلق المشروع في نيسان/أبريل 2005
It has three core components. Obviously, science is a big part of it.
وله ثلاث محاور رئيسة، والعلوم -كما يبدو- جزء كبير من المشروع،
The field research that we're doing around the world with indigenous peoples.
العمل الميداني الذي نقوم به حول العالم مع السكان الأصليين،
People who have lived in the same location for a long period of time
الناس الذين عاشوا في نفس المكان لفترة طويلة من الزمن،
retain a connection to the place where they live
الحفاظ على صلة بالمكان الذي يعيشون فيه
that many of the rest of us have lost.
والتي فقدها معظمنا،
So my ancestors come from all over northern Europe.
إذا فأسلافي أتوا من كل شمال أوروبا،
I live in the Eastern Seaboard of North America when I'm not traveling.
أنا أقطن على الساحل الشرقي لأمريكا الشمالية عندما لا أكون مسافرا،
Where am I indigenous to? Nowhere really. My genes are all jumbled up.
أين يعود أصلي؟ لا مكان حقا، إن جيناتي موزعة حول العالم،
But there are people who retain that link to their ancestors
لكن هناك من أبقى على صلته بأسلافه
that allows us to contextualize the DNA results.
ما يسمح لنا بتأطير نتائج الحمض النووي.
That's the focus of the field research,
هذا هو محور التركيز للبحث الميداني،
the centers that we've set up all over the world --
إن المراكز التي أقمناها حول أنحاء العالم،
10 of them, top population geneticists.
10 منهم من أفضل مراكز علم الجينات،
But, in addition, we wanted to open up this study to anybody around the world.
ولكن إضافة إلي ذلك، أردنا أن نفتح المشاركة للجميع من كل أنحاء العالم،
How often do you get to participate in a big scientific project?
كم مرة تتاح لك المشاركة في مشروع علمي ضخم؟
The Human Genome Project, or a Mars Rover mission.
مثل مشروع الجينوم البشري أو مهمة استكشاف المريخ؟
In this case, you actually can.
في هذه المرة يمكنك المشاركة.
You can go onto our website, Nationalgeographic.com/genographic.
يمكنك الذهاب إلى موقعنا على النت: Nationalgeographic.com/genographic
You can order a kit. You can test your own DNA.
ثم تطلب حقيبة لاختبار الحمض النووي خاصتك،
And you can actually submit those results to the database,
و تقوم بإرسال النتائج إلى قاعدة بياناتنا،
and tell us a little about your genealogical background,
وتخبرنا قليلاًعن خلفيتك الجينية المنطقية،
have the data analyzed as part of the scientific effort.
ونحن نقوم بتحليلها كجزء من الجهد العلمي.
Now, this is all a nonprofit enterprise, and so the money that we raise,
إن هذا المشروع غير ربحي، لذا فكل الأرباح
after we cover the cost of doing the testing and making the kit components,
بعد تغطية تكاليف الاختبار والحقيبة
gets plowed back into the project.
يتم ضخها مجددا إلى المشروع.
The majority going to something we call the Legacy Fund.
غالبيته سيذهب إلى ما نسميه صندوق الإرث،
It's a charitable entity, basically a grant-giving entity
إنه كيان خيري، لإعطاء المنح
that gives money back to indigenous groups around the world
لإعادة الأموال إلى السكان الأصليين حول العالم،
for educational, cultural projects initiated by them.
في مجال التعليم، المشاريع الثقافية، المنطلقة من أنفسهم.
They apply to this fund in order to do various projects,
بإمكانهم التقديم للصندوق لتمويل عدد مختلف من المشاريع،
and I'll show you a couple of examples.
وسأعرض مثالين،
So how are we doing on the project? We've got about 25,000 samples
أين وصلنا بمشروعنا؟ حسنا، لدينا 25000 عينة،
collected from indigenous people around the world.
مجمعة من سكان أصليين من حول العالم.
The most amazing thing has been the interest on the part of the public;
الشيء الأكثر روعة هو اهتمام الجمهور،
210,000 people have ordered these participation kits
210000 شخصا طلبوا حقائب ليشاركوا،
since we launched two years ago,
منذ أن أطلقنا المشروع من سنتين،
which has raised around five million dollars,
الذي جمع 5 ملايين دولار،
the majority of which, at least half, is going back into the Legacy Fund.
ذهب معظمها -نصفها على الأقل- إلى صندوق الإرث،
We've just awarded the first Legacy Grants totaling around 500,000 dollars.
وقدمنا أول منحة من منح الإرث بمبلغ 500 ألف دولار،
Projects around the world -- documenting oral poetry in Sierra Leone,
مشاريع حول العالم وثقت الشعر الشفوي في سيراليون،
preserving traditional weaving patterns in Gaza,
تحافظ على تقاليد الحياكة في غزة،
language revitalization in Tajikistan, etc., etc.
إعادة إنعاش لغة في طاجاكستان، إلخ، إلخ...
So the project is going very, very well,
إذا المشروع نجح نجاحا باهرا،
and I urge you to check out the website and watch this space.
لذا أنا أحثكم لزيارة موقعنا لمشاهدة هذه المساحة،
Thank you very much.
شكرا لكم جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)